"Boosting Heart Nerve Control"
Next, everyone feel for your pulse.
Stick your hand out, thumbs up,
feel for the knobby bone
at the top of your wrist.
Then, if you slide your hand down
across the front of your wrist,
you’ll feel these like
strands of spaghetti—
those are the tendons in your wrist.
If you lightly feel between the
knobby bone and that first tendon,
you should feel your pulse.
Got it?
Okay, now we’re going
to feel what happens
to our pulse when we take a deep breath.
We’re going to try it twice.
Try to feel what happens to
your pulse when you inhale,
and when you exhale.
All right, here we go—
slow inhale…
slow exhale.
One more time…
What happened when you
breathed in and breathed out?
You should have felt your pulse
speed up when you breathe in
and slow down when you breathe out --
that’s called heart rate variability,
and it’s a very good thing.
That’s a measure of the control
our nerves have over our heart.
This is the survival curve for
people after a heart attack.
With good heart rate variability,
9 out of 10 people are
still alive four years later.
But with bad heart rate variability,
in that time period,
half drop dead from sudden cardiac death.
Is there anything we can do
to improve our neurological
control over our heart?
A landmark article this year in the
American Journal of Clinical Nutrition
found that there was
only one type of food
that could significantly improve
our heart rate variability.
Is it citrus fruits,
omega-3s,
or dark green leafy vegetables?
Let’s look at the graph.
Here’s the level at which
statistical significance is reached.
Let’s see which one makes it.
Eating just a half serving
of greens every day
significantly improved
neuronal heart control—
which may be why studies in the past
have suggested a quarter
cup of greens a day
could cut our risk of having
a heart attack by 67%!